Chaitanya Kapoor

chaitanya.7.kapoor@gmail.com

github.com/ckapoor7

□ ckapoor7.github.io

(Nationality: Citizen of the United States of America)

Research Interests

My research interests lie at the intersection of Deep Learning and Neuroscience, aiming to understand and reverse engineer neural computation. I aim to develop computational models of cognitive neural circuits, with an overarching goal of designing efficient, biologically-constrained learning algorithms.

Education

University of California, San Diego

Aug. 2024 - Present

Post-Baccalaureate Student (NeuroML Group)

La Jolla, CA

Advisor: Meenakshi Khosla

Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Jan. 2024 - July 2024

Visiting Student (Senseable Intelligence Group)

Cambridge, MA

Thesis: LUMIN: Light-sheet Microscopy Analysis Unified with Distributed and Domain-Randomized

Generative Models

Advisor: Satrajit Ghosh

Birla Institute of Technology and Science, Pilani

B.E. (Hons.) in Electrical and Electronics engineering

Nov. 2020 - July 2024

Pilani, India

Honors & Awards

04/24NeuroMatch Academy: Computational Neuroscience Summer School

02/24COSYNE 2024: Undergraduate Travel Grant Award

04/23OxML 2023: ML × Health Summer School, Oxford Mathematical Institute

Publications

Bridging Critical Gaps in Convergent Learning: How Representational Alignment Evolves Across Layers, Training, and Distribution Shifts

C. Kapoor, S. Srivastava, M. Khosla

(Under review) - preprint

Multiplexed Expansion Revealing for Imaging Multiprotein Nanostructures in Healthy and **Diseased Brain**

J. Kang, M. Schroeder, Y. Lee, C. Kapoor, E. Yu, T. B. Tarr, K. Titterton, M. Zeng, D. Park, E. Niederst, D. Wei, E. S. Boyden

Nature Communications, 2024 - paper, code, news story

RnR-ExM: Robust Non-Rigid Registration Challenge for Expansion Microscopy Volumes

E. Besier, R. Zhang, Y. Bando, Y. Quéméner, C. Kapoor, M. Alawi, M. Hoffman, A. Dalca, A.

Casamitjana, I. Arganda-Carreras, E. S. Boyden, H. Pfister, D. Wei

IEEE International Symposium on Biomedical Imaging (IEEE ISBI), 2023 - code, website

Attention-enabled Deep Neural Network for Enhancing UAV-Captured Pavement Imagery in Poor Visibility

C. Kapoor, A. Warrier, M. Singh, P. Narang, H. Puppala, R. Srinivas, A. P. Singh IEEE Multimedia Information Processing and Retrieval (IEEE MIPR), 2023 - paper

Fast and Lightweight UAV-based Road Image Enhancement Under Multiple Low-Visibility Conditions

C. Kapoor, A. Warrier, M. Singh, P. Narang, H. Puppala, R. Srinivas, A. P. Singh PerCom Workshops (PerSASN 2023) - paper

Dense Residual Networks for Gaze Mapping on Indian Roads

C. Kapoor, K. Kumar, S. Vishnoi, S. Ramanathan

preprint

Research Experience

NeuroML Lab Aug. 2024 – Present

Supervisor: Prof. Meenakshi Khosla

La Jolla, CA

• Leading the investigation in convergence of learnt representations of artificial and biological neural networks.

- Exploring network invariances across network layers and training, by identifying the *minimal* set of transformations to align representations.
- Examining responses of networks to out-of-distribution stimulus to uncover shared learning principles between systems.

Talmo Lab May 2023 – Aug. 2024

Supervisor: Dr. Talmo Pereira

Salk Institute, La Jolla, CA

- Worked on the development of methods for pose estimation and tracking to quantify animal behavior through robust tracking of anatomical landmarks in 3D.
- Designed algorithms utilizing projective geometry to create inputs for a CNN that leverages geometric reasoning.

Senseable Intelligence Group

Jan. 2024 – July 2024

Supervisor: Prof. Satrajit Ghosh

Massachusetts Institute of Technology, MA

- Developed a distributed framework for large-scale (≈ 1TiB) image segmentation for light-sheet microscopy images.
- Designed a domain-randomized generative model, using spherical harmonics to synthesize cortical sections of *ex-vivo* human brains to enable zero-shot segmentation.
- Worked on designing few-shot, spatially guided semantic segmentation algorithms for MRI segmentation.
- Proposed the use of a topologically aware Graph Neural Network which is capable of encoding spatial and anatomical constraints.

Synthetic Neurobiology Group

Feb. 2022 - Jan. 2024

Supervisors: Prof. Ed Boyden, Prof. Donglai Wei

Massachusetts Institute of Technology, MA

- Worked on the development of a *generalist* 3D segmentation model for Expansion Microscopy (ExM) volumes for various animal species.
- Proposed a human-in-the-loop feedback learning mechanism, built on top of an existing deep learning framework, NucMM.
- Worked on developing a new joint-intensity and point-based, high throughput image registration algorithms having nanoscale precision (10-40 nm) for Multiplexed Expansion Revealing (multiExR). This work has been published at Nature Communications.

Invited Talks and Tutorials

02/24 Automating behavior quantification using deep learning, COSYNE 2024

06/23 SIS Symposium, Harvard SEAS, Seeing Beyond the Camera

Teaching Experience

Department of Mathematics, BITS Pilani

August 2023 - Dec. 2023

Teaching Assistant

Pilani, India

• Undergraduate TA: assisted with the course Combinatorial Mathematics (MATH F421)

Students Mentored

• Chanyoung Park: Undergraduate Student at UC San Diego

Technical Skills

Languages: Python, C, MATLAB, Unix Shell Scripting, LATEX

Technologies/Frameworks: Keras, Tensorflow, Numpy, PyTorch, Git, OpenCV